Contact

joapen@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/jpenafernand (LinkedIn) joapen.com (Blog)

Top Skills

Go-to-Market Strategy
Operational Strategy
Cross-functional Team Leadership

Languages

Spanish (Native or Bilingual)

English

French

German

Certifications

ITIL V3 Foundation

Neo4j Fundamentals

Técnico en prevención de riesgos laborales, Grado Medio

Cobit 5 Foundation

Awareness in Wardley Mapping

Publications

DREAM: Mi Six Sigma casero del ahorro e inversión

Joaquín Peña Fernández

Business and Technology Strategist | 20+ years of experience in Consulting & Operations | Black Belt Six Sigma | Mapping Expert | Researcher & Author

Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, United States

Summary

I am an experienced leader, holding a variety of strategic and operational roles in technology over the past the past 22 years.

I love working on strategy. I love finding solutions to difficult problems. I excel at detecting new opportunities and market trends.

I have a special interest in bringing next generation technologies into organizations in the form of deliverable and profitable solutions.

I take a data informed approach while working in a human centric way.

I firmly believe in the power and the necessity of great communication as a key leadership skill. I communicate in a warm yet structured way to facilitate collaboration and coordination within my team, cross functionally and with senior leadership and board members.

One of my strengths is to guide and motivate my teams to successfully execute within the context of a larger strategic vision. I lead by example and uphold a firm committed to deliver.

I have a professional interest and intellectual curiosity that draws me to work with technology. What excites me about technology is how technological developments and innovation can enable and even fundamentally change the way we work, live and do business.

At the same time I truly enjoy working with people and excel at leadership and team building. While it is a challenge, it is also a pleasure for me to focus on creating a team culture that leads to a well-functioning, reliable and high performing team of effective and engaged employees.

I publish regularly on business strategy, technological innovation, and investing here: https://joapen.com/

I regularly speak at conferences on topics related to strategy and mapping.

I am a recognized expert on Wardley maps (https://mapasdewardley.com/). This is a visual tool used for representing a business environment, the factors involved, tracking how they relate to each other, the evolution over time, and serves not only as a representation or working tool, but also as a communication tool for discussion and decision making.

I designed and deliver the following course "...." focused on teaching professionals how to incorporate mapping tools to their strategy work through practical application and hands on work.

I am a published author of books on business strategy and investing (available in English and Spanish):

- Draw your company Strategy: https://www.amazon.com/Draw-your-company-strategy-practical/dp/B09QFJ4QDG/
- Cuaderno de Trabajo para dibujar estrategias: https:// www.amazon.com/Cuaderno-trabajo-para-dibujar-estrategias-ebook/ dp/B0BPQTLCYS

Experience

Mapas

Founder & Director January 2021 - Present (2 years 4 months)

Expert in designing and developing business strategy, technology strategy, operational strategy and go to market strategy (GTM) using a visual tool called Wardley Maps.

 Authored of the book, Draw your company strategy published in English and Spanish.

- Competitive analysis of companies, describing the actual landscape, anticipation of potential gameplays, and foresight of different scenarios.
- Drive the definition and the execution of strategic playbook.
- Revision of strategic plans, providing feedback for executive lead with areas for improvement.
- Analysis of IT architecture and design with recommendations of improvement for adapting the IT landscape to the business challenges.
- Speaker on Business Strategy & Mapping Frameworks.
- Creator of the Course Acelera tu Aprendizaje en Mapas de Wardley (https://mapasdewardley.com/estrategia/acelera-tu-aprendizaje/).
- Conducting research to identify new economic patterns in the manufacturing industry using data driven and strategy mapping tools).
- Event sponsor at https://wardleymapsforbusiness.com/

DXC Technology

Senior Program Manager Global Large Scale Transformations April 2017 - Present (6 years 1 month)

Ownership of the programs from offering through delivery.

- Pre-contract phase: I build the program structure during the sales process, defend the deal for approval internally and in front of the customer.
- Delivery phase: Go through due diligence, build global project teams, oversee execution of projects under the program, ensure financial targets are met, lead the change management effort, etc.

A key to my success in this role is my focus on defining clear and complete conditions for each contract where the scope of work and commitments of each party are specified. This facilitates the execution of the delivery phase.

Lean Portfolio Management ramp-up.

CSC

10 years 3 months

Engagement Manager EMEA | Technology | Engineering | Data Science July 2014 - March 2017 (2 years 9 months)

Sevilla Area, Spain

- I create and manage a relationship with customers that enable me to grow a portfolio of to \$20M, own the opportunity management cycle: Prospect-Evaluate-Propose-Execute.
- I drive the delivery building and guiding the teams to ensure fulfilment of all commitments to the client.

• I put focus on governance creating an account plan, opportunities to be pursued, partners agreements, etc. (Lean Portfolio Management model).

Portfolio Manager EMEA Manufacturing & Chemical Industry February 2010 - June 2014 (4 years 5 months)

- Accountable for Service Delivery, Business Development and P&L
- Managing a portfolio of applications and assets with a team located in different locations.

Head of PMO

December 2008 - January 2010 (1 year 2 months)

Lead a team of 28 project, epic & program managers. Coach, mentor & develop members of the team. Work on specific proposals where a PMO solution was required.

Project Manager & Service Manager September 2007 - December 2008 (1 year 4 months)

Leading a Service support where mainly my responsibilities were:

- * Understands customer goals and requirements, prioritize the incoming tasks and manages customer expectations and dependencies.
- * Provides challenging environment, directs and motivates the project team, and establishes and effective climate for achieving positive working relations with other stakeholders.
- * Coordinates recommendations for technology solutions that address client requirements identified during the project life-cycle.
- * Achieves contractual commitments related to quality, cost, and schedule. Facilitates the review of risks and develops appropriate risk mitigation plans. Write & deliver proposals.
- * Overview the resolution of the different tasks with the team work.
- * Provide the customer a proper scoreboard where they can know the status of their Service (coordinated with ASM).
- * Review Service Supports contracts.

Apart of Dispatcher responsibility I have also lead some initiatives:

- * REACh, Communication Module. Project Manager of this module.
- * Domino.doc Data Migration. Project Manager.
- * Proposal for Blackberry solution for DuPont P&IP Pricing Approval Cycle Time improvement system.

Senior Application Developer January 2007 - August 2007 (8 months)

- Implementation of solutions for Applications requests from the customer.
- Definition of technical solutions and technical offers.
- Architecture descriptions of different environments.
- Owner of the lifecycle of the applications (products).

Telvent Outsourcing, S.A.
Project Manager
January 2005 - January 2007 (2 years 1 month)

Mainly my responsibilities were:

- * To elaborate and deliver offers and project plans to the clients.
- * I worked with the suppliers at the labor of looking for new resources, seeing the yield of the current ones, processing the purchase orders and signing the invoices.
- * To manage the team under my responsibility, having weekly meetings to review every project . All our applications are developed with access via Lotus Notes Client and Web Client.
- * Economic control of the projects.

Significant Projects:

- * Unified Workflow: Workflow management tool where you can define the workflow and roles. These definitions are run in the application and the resultant information is used to store documents in each container and is used to extract stats.
- * Legal Consultant's office: This tool manages all proceedings that the legal consultant's office uses.
- * MAE: Evolutionary Adaptive Maintenance. Its a compound of decisions on the corporate applications of the company with the purpose of improving these applications with evolutionary changes without big investments.
- * Deployment of the corporate applications in TNA: Management of the deployment of all corporate applications of Abengoa in Telvent North America (TNA).
- * Proposal files: Tool that manages all information related to a proposal: economic summary, approvals, technical information...
- * Guarantee & Factoring: This tool manages the requests to the financial department in issues related to Guarantee & Factoring.

- * Warehouse & Shipment: Application that manages the stock of a warehouse, the entries and outputs in the Telvent's warehouse.
- * Purchasing of Bioenergy: Approval management of the purchasing of Abengoa Bioenergy Corporation. Tool with interfaces with Baan and agree with SOX normative.

www.abengoa.com www.telvent.com

Telvent Outsourcing S.A. Product Manager February 2003 - January 2005 (2 years)

February 2003 - January 2005 (2 years)

- Analysis of business needs with customer
- Definition of business analysis needs.
- Definition of technical solutions.
- Implementation of solutions.
- Define the architecture of complex and distributed web Apps
- Construction of common JavaScript libraries for the development team.

Abentel Telecomunicaciones S.A.

Application Analyst

April 2001 - February 2003 (1 year 11 months)

Analysis of business needs with customer

Definition of business analysis needs.

Definition of technical solutions.

Implementation of solutions

Promainsur S.A.

Lotus Notes Development

July 2000 - April 2001 (10 months)

Definition of technical solutions.

Implementation of solutions for web (html, CSS and JavaScript) and lotus notes client.

Administration of development and production servers.

Education

Universidad de Cádiz

BS Industrial Engineering, Electrical and Electronics Engineering · (1995 - 1999)

Seth Godin's altMBA altMBA54, Seth Godin's Akimbo Workshops · (2023)